Hello everyone! Earlier we had a look at the 2 step process of saving data into git. That is we first stage changes with "git add"
and then commit those changes with "git commit". However, one could wonder if there is a shortcut?
That is omit "git add" and commit changes directly into the repository. In simple cases there is.
Let's have a look at a typical situation. I open a project with a blank status, that is with no changes.
I then proceed to modify a few files. Let's say I made a change here and here.
Renamed hello function to helloGitty.
Now, if we look at the status, we see our unstaged changes.
In order to commit these changes we can type "git commit" with "--all" option or "-a" for brevity. And let's add a commit message here as well.
"-m" could be used separately or together like in this instance.
flag "-a" would force the commit command to take all changes from the working directory,
stage them and commit to the repository.
We end up doing two actions with one command: staging and committing.
At the same time there is one serious restriction:
"-a" ignores files not tracked by git. That is if I create a file named, let's say, "new.html" and then execute "git status" - here is the new file.
"git commit -a". You see, nothing happened. That is because the file is not tracked.
In other words flag "-a" adds to commit a preliminary step at which it stages all changes from the working directory,
but only for those files that are already in the index. In our case for these.
It then makes a usual commit with the new index. It is very useful when you start working with a project with a fresh status,
made chages to existing files and quickly committed your changes.
I reverted previously made changes. Let's have a look at another case.
Let's suppose we already have changes in our project. Something goes on here, there,
may be some changes are already staged.
And let's suppose that we need to open a third file and add some changes in it.
For instance, we want to ignore all log files and commit these changes right away because they are very important,
fix a typo, and must appear in the project immediately.
Here is the situation: I have changes in my working directory, I have staged changes, but I only want to commit these changes here.
There is nothing easier: "git commit", various parameters
and a path. In our case it is a single file. But you can indicate many paths, including directories, and voila.
Commit takes changes from the given paths, stages them and saves into our repository.
Note well that if we have a look at "git status" once again you will notice that all other changes remained as they were.
Commit only worked for changes under the given path.
The same restriction applies here as for the flag "-a": files not tracked by git will be ignored.
So, if I add once again a file named "new.html"
and try to call "git commit" on it, nothing would happen as you can see.
We had a look at the "-a" flag for staging all changes for tracked fiels.
Indicated paths to the files that must be committed but it only works for files tracked by git.
One may wonder why it only works for tracked files?
It is very simple.
It is done on purpose to avoid unintentionally adding unwanted files to the repository.
We do not want any temporary files or results of a build. Anything could happen.
On the other hand sometimes we want to commit all changes made including untracked files.
There is no single command for this in git but we could create an alias like this.
Its usage is very simple: we go to the required directory and call "git commit --all"
We could add additinal parameters. They would be appened to the end of our alias,
that is for the command "git commit"
This would add the content of the current directory to the index and call "git commit" on it.
Another variation of this recipe is "git add -A"
This flag is rarely used. If we compare it to with the previous example, it only add the current directory.
For instance if we go to the src subdirectory the "." would stand for this directory.
Where as "git add - A", whereever we might call it from,
would stage all changes starting from the root of the project.
Bam - everything is staged.
And if you bothered to call "git status" you would see that not only existing files have been staged but also files that were not tracked previously.
The complete exaple of using this alias would look like this: "git commit --all"
followed by additional parameters for "commit".
Note well that you should not normally do as I just did because I took all changes,
mixed them up in one big commit and saved to git.
Developers who do like this, are sometimes jockingly said to be using git like a time machine.
We could always roll back to previous commits, but it would be very difficult to navigate through the development process.
If we however know for sure that our changes form a good commit then why not? This alias is quite pertinent. We could use it.
We had a look at three ways to commit without an explicit call to "add".
The first one: the "-a" flag automatically stagies changes in the working directory but only in those files that
were already tracked by git. It is very useful when we start working with a project with a fresh status, made a few changes and want to commit them quickly.
Second one: explicitly provide paths to the "commit". The result would be the same but only for the give paths.
It is very useful when we have several unstaged changes in our project but we only want to commit a few files.
Git would ignore other paths.
And, finally, if we wanted to commit untracked files we could create an alias.
This one for committing changes in a given directory and this one - for the whole project.
We must always be careful not to commit unnecessary files but in trivial situations such aliases could be useful.